A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Mora McLean FA1467
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Mora McLean
1957, 1992-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
McLean, Mora L.
Ford Foundation
FA1467
2.75 Cubic Feet 7 boxes (6 letter document containers, 1 legal document containers)
Biographical / Historical
Mora McLean joined the Ford Foundation in 1986 as a program officer for the Minority Rights and Opportunities office within the Human Rights and Social Justice program. The Minority Rights and Opportunities program aimed to improve minority access to employment, education, housing, and the political process, by supporting civil rights organizations engaged in litigation, education, and advocacy. In 1990, she became a representative to the West Africa/Nigeria office in Lagos, and in 1995, she became Deputy Director of Africa and Middle East Programs. She left the Foundation in 1996 to become President/CEO for the Africa-America Institute (AAI).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, trip itineraries, inter-office memos, files related to trustee meetings, reports, and grant-related materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2018:067.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series:
1. Program Officer and Representative Office Files, 1992-1996
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation Africa
- Program Officer and Representative Office Files, 1957, 1992-1996; 1; 2.75 Cubic Feet 1 legal document box and 6 letter boxes
  - Report of Ford Foundation Mission to Africa (Cataloged Report #000579), 1957 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Report on the Theatre Outreach Activities of the Performance Studio Workshop (Theatre in Transition) (2 folders), 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Education and Culture Program - 651/Kings Majestic (2 folders), 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Education and Culture Program - Museum for African Art, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Education and Culture Program - Campus Diversity Initiative, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - South Africa - Law Related Grantees, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - South Africa Trip (4 folders), 1995 July (Box 1, Folder 9-11, Box 2, Folder 12)
  - South Africa Trip Itinerary, 1996 January (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mozambique Trip Itinerary, 1995 November (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Trustees Meeting - South Africa, 1996 March (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Social Summit (U.N.) (3 folders), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - South Africa Free Elections (SAFE) Fund, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, South Africa and Namibia Trip - Agenda and Planning, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Arts and Humanities Issues (South Africa) - 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Alice Brown Consultancy - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Credit and Enterprise - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Development Aid (South Africa) - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 May (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Higher Education - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 May (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Land Issues (South Africa) - March 1996 Trustees Meeting (2 folders), 1995 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Mozambique - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - NGOs (South Africa) - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Philanthropy (South Africa) - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Suggested Reading - March 1996 Trustees Meeting, 1995 November (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Text for June 1995 Board Meeting, 1995 May (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - US Policy Toward South Africa - March 1996 Board Meeting, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Women's Health Issues (South Africa) - March 1996 Board Meeting, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Tutu, Naomi, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - UN Commission on the Status of Women, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - US Aid in Africa, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - US Policy Toward Africa, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Violence, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Winrock International (3 folders), 1995 (Box 3, Folder 38, Box 4, Folder 39-40)
  - Correspondence A-L, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence M-Z, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1993 July-December (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Memos (2 folders), 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 44, Box 5, Box 45)
  - Memos, 1993 October-December (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Memos, 1994 July-October (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Memos, 1994 January-June (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence A-L, 1994 January-June (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence M-Z, 1994 January-June (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1994 July-September (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence (2 folders), 1994 October-December (Box 5, Folder 52-53)
  - Women and Conflict Resolution, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - World Bank, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Africa and Middle East (AME) Program (Background) - Field Office Profiles, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Africa and Middle East (AME) Program (Background) - Functions of Regional Office, undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Africa and Middle East (AME) Program (Background) - Overview of the Ford Foundation AME Office, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Africa and Middle East (AME) Program (Background) - Text for June '95 Board Meeting AME Description, 1995 May (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) Presentations - African Economic Research Consortium (AERC), 1995 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) Presentations - Cairo University, 1995 April (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) Presentations - Emory University, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) Presentations - Film Society of Lincoln Center, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) Presentations - Joint Education Trust (JET), 1995 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) Presentation - Kenya Women Finance Trust, Ltd., 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Scope and Contents
    Grant No.: 9001327
  - Consultancies, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 75)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Sensitive Materials
  - Consultancies, 1995-1966 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Higher Education Consultancy, 1992-1996 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Africa and Middle East Strategy (2 folders), 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 68-69)
  - Africa and Middle East Strategy Paper-Field Office Comments, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Trustees Beijing Presentation, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Spending Patterns (Africa and Middle East, New York and Field Office), 1995 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    Grant No.: 9451077
  - Program Papers - Eastern and Southern Africa (2 folders), 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 73-74)